Guide to the Archives of the Soviet communist party and Soviet state microfilm collection: Russian State Archives of Social and Political History (Rossiiskii gosudarstvennyi arkhiv sotsialno-politicheskoi istorii - RGASPI)
Hoover Institution Archives
- Fond 17, The Central Committee of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union records, 1903-1965; 1971; 2,457 reels
  - Opis 76: Administration of Affairs of the TsK KPSS. Department of Budget and Finance, 1939-1955, 262 reels) (Reel 2.328-2.406, Reel 2.735-2.758, Reel 2.871-2.899, Reel 2.1096-2.1212, Reel 2.1487-2.1497, Reel 2.1580)
    - Financial report of Primorskii kraikom; consolidated party budgets for and financial reports of Pskovskii, Rostovskii, Riazanskii, Saratovskii, Sakhalinskii, Sverdlovskii, Severo-Osetinskii, and Smolenskii obkoms; consolidated party budget of Stavropolskii kraikom, 1955 (Reel 2.1490, File 2597-2614)
    - Financial report of Stavropolskii kraikom; consolidated party budgets for and financial reports of Stalingradskii, Tambovskii, Tatarskii, Tomskii, Tuvinskii, and Tulskii obkoms and of the TsK KP of Tadzhikistan and of Turkmenistan, 1955 (Reel 2.1491, File 2615-2631)
    - Consolidated party budgets for and financial reports of Tiumenskii and Udmurtskii obkoms and of the TsK KP of Uzbekistan; consolidated party budget of the TsK KP of Ukraine (vols. 1-2), 1955 (Reel 2.1492, File 2632-2639)
    - Consolidated party budget of the TsK KP of Ukraine (vol. 3); financial reports of the TsK KP of Ukraine and of the Higher Party School under the TsK VKP of Ukraine; consolidated party budgets for and financial reports of Ulianovskii, Cheliabinskii, Chitinskii, Chkalovskii, and Chuvashskii obkoms and of Khabarovskii kraikom, 1955 (Reel 2.1493, File 2640-2654)
    - Consolidated party budgets for and financial reports of the TsK KP of Estonia and of Yakutskii and Yaroslavskii obkoms; memoranda from instructors of the Department of Budget and Finance of the TsK KPSS Administration of Affairs regarding results of auditing financial and economic activities of obkoms, kraikoms, and central committees of the parties of union republics presented alphabetically geographic name of party organization; estimate sheets for and statements from the Academy of Social Sciences under the TsK KPSS; estimate sheets for and correspondence of the Higher Party School under the TsK KPSS, 1955 (Reel 2.1494, File 2655-2668)
    - Annual report of the V.I. Lenin Central Museum; balance sheet for the Institute of the Party History under the TsK KP of Ukraine; financial reports of the Kiev branch of the V.I. Lenin Central Museum and of the publishing houses of the newspapers Altaiskaia pravda and Kommuna under Voronezhskii obkom; industrial/financial plan for the printing and publishing houses of the newspapers Pravda, Altaiskaia pravda, Kommuna under Voronezhskii obkom, and Vostochno-Sibirskaia pravda under Irkutskii obkom; industrial/ financial plan for and report of Gospolitizdat (State Publishing House for Political Literature); draft plan, annual report, and draft and final versions of industrial/financial plan for the joint newspaper/magazine publishing house under the TsK KP of Azerbaijan, 1955 (Reel 2.1495, File 2668-2681)
    - Annual reports of the publishing houses Sovetskaia Kuban under Krasnodarskii kraikom and Volzhskaia kommuna under Kuibyshevskii obkom; industrial/financial plan for the publishing house Volzhskaia kommuna under Kuibyshevskii obkom, Lenizdat (Leningradskii State Publishing House), and the Molotovskii provincial (oblastnoi) publishing house Zvezda and for the publishing and printing houses Moskovskaia pravda and Moskovskii rabochii; estimate sheet and technical/industrial/financial plans for the publishing house Krasnyi Kurgan and for the printing house of the newspaper Zvezda under Molotovskii obkom; report and technical/industrial/financial plan for the publishing house Kurskaia pravda; registers reflecting implementation of the industrial/financial plan by the publishing house Moskovskaia pravda, 1955 (Reel 2.1496, File 2682-2696)
    - Major indexes of the industrial/financial plan for the publishing and printing houses Moskovskaia pravda; estimating sheet/financial plan and main indexes of the industrial/financial plan for the publishing house of the newspaper Sovetskaia Sibir under Novosibirskii obkom; financial report of the newspaper publishing house Rabochii put under Smolenskii obkom; industrial/financial plans for and reports of the publishing houses of the newspapers Stalinskoe znamia under Penzenskii obkom and Molot Rostovskii obkom; industrial/financial plan for the house and editorial board of the newspaper Molot under Rostovskii obkom, for the publishing and printing houses Kommunist under Saratovskii obkom, for the publishing house Uralskii rabochii under Sverdlovskii obkom and publishing house of the newspaper Stavropolskaia pravda; annual report of the joint publishing house for Kzyl Uzbekistan, Pravda Vostoka, and Uzbekistani Surkh under the TsK KP of Uzbekistan, 1955 (Reel 2.1497, File 2697-2710)
    - Annual report of the joint publishing house for Kzyl Uzbekistan, Pravda Vostoka, and Uzbekistani Surkh under the TsK KP of Uzbekistan (cont.); technical/industrial/financial plan for the joint publishing house under the TsK KP of Uzbekistan, for the printing office of the publishing house Radianska Ukraina under the TsK KP of Ukraine, and for the Kamenskii (oblastnoi) provincial publishing house industrial/ financial plan for the publishing house Radianska Ukraina, for the newspaper/magazine publishing and printing houses Cheliabinskii rabochii, and for the publishing and printing houses Chkalovskaia kommuna; annual reports of the publishing houses Ulianovskaia pravda and Vostochno-Sibirskaia pravda under Irkutskii obkom, and of the publishing and printing houses Chkalovskaia kommuna; organizational charts with salary indication and list of monthly salaries for the employees of the publishing house Kommunist under the TsK KP of Georgia, 1955 (Reel 2.1580, File 2710-2722)
  - Opis 77: Administration of Affairs of the TsK KPSS. Department of Budget and Finance, 1939-1963, 56 reels) (Reel 2.407-2.462)
    Opis 77 (259 files on 56 reels) consists mainly of consolidated party budgets, organizational charts, and other financial documents issued by the Department of Budget and Finance of the Administration of Affairs of the TsK KPSS in 1939-1955, though some files contain documents issued in 1955-1963. It also contains materials related to the wages paid to the party members dispatched to fight German fascists in partisan detachments or performing special tasks behind German lines during World War II and to the process of granting pensions to those disabled while in partisan detachments or while performing special tasks and to the families of partisans, of those performing special tasks, and of those who perished or were missing performing special tasks. The Russian finding aid can be found on reel 2.22.
    Additional register issued by the Department of Budget and Finance
    - Budgets for local party organizations (part 1 and 2), 1939 (Reel 2.407, File 1-2)
    - Estimates of expenses for party propaganda and agitation; budgets for local party organizations presented alphabetically (vol. 1: "À-Ì"; vol. 2: "Í-Î" in Russian), 1940 (Reel 2.408, File 3-5)
    - Budgets for local party organizations presented alphabetically (vol. 2: "Î-ß"); consolidated party budgets for 1941 and 1942, 1941-1942 (Reel 2.409, File 5-8)
    - Consolidated party budgets for 1942 (cont.), and 1943 (vols. 1-2), 1942-1943 (Reel 2.410, File 8-10)
    - Consolidated party budgets for 1943 (vol. 2, cont.) and 1944 (vol. 1: "À-È"; vol. 2: " Ê" in Russian), 1943-1944 (Reel 2.411, File 10-12)
    - Consolidated party budget for (vol. 2: "Ê-Ì"; vol. 3, "Í-Ò"; vol. 4: "Ó-X" in Russian), 1944 (Reel 2.412, File 12-14)
    - Consolidated party budgets for 1944 (vol. 4: "X- ß" in Russian) and 1945 (vol. 1: "À-È"; vol. 2: " Ê-Ì" in Russian), 1944-1945 (Reel 2.413, File 14-16)
    - Consolidated party budgets for 1945 (vol. 2: "M" (cont.); vol. 3: "Í-Ò"; vol. 4: " Ó- ß" in Russian); organizational charts with salary indications for primary party organizations, 1945 (Reel 2.414, File 16-19)
    - Organizational charts with salary indications for primary party organizations (cont.); report about the implementation of the 1945 party budget; consolidated 1946 party budgets for the central committees of union republics, 1945 and 1946 (Reel 2.415, File 19-21)
    - Consolidated party budgets for the central committees of union republics, kraikoms, and obkoms, 1946 (Reel 2.416, File 21-23)
    - Consolidated party budgets for obkoms; organizational charts with salary indications and salary fund for personnel (partiinye rabotniki) of primary party organizations of the city of Moscow; organizational charts with salary indications for party organizations presented in alphabetical order by party organization ("À-Ë" in Russian), 1946 (Reel 2.417, File 24-27)
    - Organizational charts with salary indications for party organizations presented in alphabetical order by party organization ("Ë-ß" in Russian); budget for the VLKSM (All-Union Young Communists League); organizational charts with salary indications for the primary party organizations and party offices at the enterprises of the city and oblast of Moscow; consolidated financial report for 1947, 1946 and 1947 (Reel 2.418, File 27-31)
    - Organizational charts with salary indications for the secretaries of the TsK VKP(b) organization and of party personnel (partiinye rabotniki) of primary party organizations (vols. 1 and 2), 1947 (Reel 2.419, File 32-33)
    - Organizational charts with salary indications for secretaries of the TsK VKP(b) organization and for party personnel (partiinye rabotniki) of primary party organizations (vol. 2, cont.); organizational charts with salary indications for the primary party organizations in the city and oblast of Moscow for 1947 and for party organizations and party officials within Moskovskii obkom of the VKP(b) as of January 1, 1947; registers for the party personnel (partiinye rabotniki) of the primary party organizations of the city and oblast of Moscow as of July 1, 1947; consolidated party budget for 1948 in alphabetical order by union republic ("À - Á" in Russian); 1947 and 1948 (Reel 2.420, File 33-37)
    - Consolidated party budget arranged in alphabetical order by union republic (vol. 1: "Á- Ë"; vols. 2-4: "Ë-C" in Russian); consolidated party budget for Ukraine (vol. 2); consolidated party budget arranged in alphabetical order by obkom (vols. 3: "A-Ä"; vol. 4: "È-K"; vol. 5: "Ë-Î"; vol. 6 "Ï-Ð" in Russian), 1948 (Reel 2.421, File 37-42)
    - Consolidated party budget arranged in alphabetical order by obkom (vol. 6: "Ð-Ñ"; vol. 7: "Ò-ß" in Russian); consolidated party budget arranged in alphabetical order by kraikom or union republic (cont.)(vols. 8: "Ì-Õ" in Russian); organizational charts with salary indications for primary party organizations ("À-Ó" in Russian), 1948 (Reel 2.422, File 42-46)
    - Organizational charts with salary indications for primary organizations ("Ó-ß" in Russian); organizational charts with salary indications for primary organizations and party personnel (partiinye rabotniki) at the enterprises of the oblast of Moscow; organizational charts with salary indications for primary organizations and party personnel (partiinye rabotniki) at the enterprises of the city and oblast of Moscow as of July 1, 1948; organizational charts with salary indications for party personnel (partiinye rabotniki) of primary party organizations in the city of Moscow for 1948; financial report on the implementation of the 1948 budget; organizational charts with salary indications for the party secretaries of the TsK and of primary party organizations, 1948 (Reel 2.423, File 46-51)
    - Organizational charts with salary indications for party secretaries of the TsK and of primary party organizations in 1948 (cont.); organizational charts with salary indications for central committees of union republics, for kraikoms, obkoms, gorkoms, and raikoms of the VKP(b), 1948 and 1949 (Reel 2.424, File 51-54)
    - Organizational charts with salary indications for gorkoms, and raikoms of the VKP(b) (cont.) and for party primary organizations, 1949 (Reel 2.425, File 54-55)
    - Organizational charts with salary indications for primary organizations of the city and oblast of Moscow; organizational charts with salary indications for primary organizations of the city and oblast of Moscow as of January 1 and July 1, 1949; consolidated budget and organizational charts with salary indications for VKP(b) (vols. 1-2), 1949 and 1950 (Reel 2.426, File 56-60)
    - Consolidated budget and organizational charts with salary indications for VKP(b) (vol. 2, cont.; vols. 3-6), 1950 (Reel 2.427, File 60-64)
    - Consolidated budget and organizational charts with salary indications for VKP(b) (vol. 6, cont.; vols. 7-8); organizational charts for secretaries of party organizations under the TsK VKP(b) and for party personnel (partiinye rabotniki) of primary party organizations, 1950 (Reel 2.428, File 64-67)
    - Organizational charts with salary indications for secretaries of party organizations under the TsK VKP(b) and personnel (partiinye rabotniki) of primary party organizations (cont.); organizational charts for party personnel (partiinye rabotniki) of primary party organizations and party offices of the city and oblast of Moscow as of January 1 and July 1, 1950; consolidated 1951 budget for the VKP(b (vol. 1), 1950 and 1951 (Reel 2.429, File 67-71)
    - Consolidated budget for the VKP(b) (vol. 1, cont.; vols. 2-4), 1951 (Reel 2.430, File 71-74)
    - Consolidated budget for the VKP(b) (vol. 4, cont.; vols. 5-7); organizational charts with salary indications for primary organizations of the VKP(b), 1951 (Reel 2.431, File 74-78)
    - Organizational charts with salary indications for primary organizations of the VKP(b) (cont.); organizational charts with salary indications for primary party organizations of the city and oblast of Moscow; organizational charts with salary indications for primary party organizations of the city and oblast of Moscow as of January 1 and July 1, 1951; organizational charts with salary indications for primary party organizations of the city and oblast of Leningrad, 1951 (Reel 2.432, File 78-82)
    - Organizational charts with salary indications for primary party organizations of the city and oblast of Leningrad (cont.), for the Ukrainian party organization and for party organizations from Azerbaijan to Yaroslavl presented alphabetically; consolidated 1952 budget arranged alphabetically by party organization of union republic (vol. 1: "A-K"; vol. 2: "Ê-Ë" in Russian), 1951 and 1952 (Reel 2.433, File 82-87)
    - Consolidated budget arranged alphabetically by party organization of union republic (vol. 2: "Ë- Ó"; vol. 3: "Ó-Ý"); consolidated budget arranged alphabetically by obkoms (vol. 8: "Ñ-ß" in Russian); organizational charts with salary indications for primary party organizations of the VKP(b), 1952 (Reel 2.434, File 87-90)
    - Organizational charts with salary indications for primary party organizations of the VKP(b)(cont.), for the Ukrainian party organization, for personnel (partiinye rabotniki) of party offices at the enterprises of the city of Moscow; organizational charts with salary indications for the personnel (partiinye rabotniki) of primary party organizations and party offices of the city and oblast of Moscow as of July 1, 1952; consolidated 1953 budget for party organizations of union republics presented alphabetically (vol. 1: "À-Ó" in Russian), 1952 and 1953 (Reel 2.435, File 90-94)
    - Consolidated budget for party organizations of union republics (vol. 1: "Ó-Ý" in Russian), kraikoms (vol. 1: "À-Õ" in Russian), and obkoms (vol. 2: "A-Ë"; vol. 3: "Ì-ß" in Russian); organizational charts with salary indications for primary organizations of the VKP(b), 1953 (Reel 2.436, File 94-97)
    - Organizational charts with salary indications for primary organizations of the VKP(b) (vol. 4; vol. 5, parts 1 and 2), 1953 (Reel 2.437, File 97-99)
    - Organizational charts with salary indications for party personnel (partiinye rabotniki) of party organizations of the central committees of union republics, kraikoms, and obkoms; registers of party personnel (partiinye rabotniki) of political departments of machine and tractor specialized stations, 1953 (Reel 2.438, File 100-103)
    - Registers of party personnel (partiinye rabotniki) of political departments of machine and tractor specialized stations (cont.); organizational charts with salary indications for rural raikoms, for primary party organizations of the Ukraine and of Moscow, and for primary party organizations and libraries of the enterprises within the Moscow party organization, 1953 (Reel 2.439, File 103-107)
    - Consolidated party budgets for central committees of union republics, kraikoms, and obkoms presented in alphabetical order ("À-Ò" in Russian), 1954 (Reel 2.440, File 108-110)
    - Consolidated party budgets for obkoms ("Ò-ß" in Russian); budget for the Ukrainian party organization; organizational charts for primary party organizations, 1954 (Reel 2.441, File 110-112)
    - Organizational charts for primary party organizations (cont.); consolidated party budgets for central committees of union republics (vols. 1-2), 1955 (Reel 2.442, File 112-114)
    - Consolidated party budgets for central committees of union republics (vol. 2, cont.), kraikoms, and obkoms (vols. 3-4), 1955 (Reel 2.443, File 114-116)
    - Consolidated party budgets for kraikoms and obkoms (vol. 5), and for the Ukrainian party organization; organizational charts for party personnel (partiinye rabotniki) of primary organizations of central committees of union republics and kraikoms, 1955 (Reel 2.444, File 117-119)
    - Organizational charts for the exempt personnel (osvobozhdennye rabotniki) of primary party organizations of central committees of union republics and kraikoms (cont.), obkoms, and for the Leningrad party organization for 1955; consolidated party budgets issued in 1940-1943 (vol. 2) and 1939-1944 (vol. 3) by the Department of Budget and Finance of the Administration of Affairs of the TsK VKP(b), 1939-1944 and 1955 (Reel 2.445, File 119-124)
    - Consolidated party budgets issued in 1939-1944 (vol. 3, cont.) and in 1945-1947 (vol. 4) by the Department of Budget and Finance of the Administration of Affairs of the TsK VKP(b); party budget arranged in alphabetical order by geographical name of party organization (Altaiskii kraikom - Kurskii obkom), 1939-1947 and 1952 (Reel 2.446, File 124-128)
    - Party budget for 1952 arranged in alphabetical order by geographical name of party organization (Kurskii obkom (cont.)- Smolenskii obkom); draft organizational charts for exempt personnel (osvobozhdennye rabotniki) of primary party organizations in 1945; 1945 and 1952 (Reel 2.447, File 128-130)
    - Draft organizational charts for exempt personnel (osvobozhdennye rabotniki) of primary party organizations in 1944 (cont.) and 1945; 1944 and 1945 (Reel 2.448, File 130-131)
    - Draft organizational charts for exempt personnel (osvobozhdennye rabotniki) of primary party organizations in 1945 (cont.) and 1946, 1945 and 1946 (Reel 2.449, File 131-132)
    - Draft organizational chart for exempt personnel (osvobozhdennye rabotniki) of primary party organizations in 1945 (cont.); materials relating to the salary and organizational charts for the party committees of the Ministry of Medium Machine-Building in 1956-1957; estimate sheets for political administrations and political departments in 1951-1960, 1945 and 1951-1960 (Reel 2.450, File 132-135)
    - Estimate sheets for political administrations (politupravleniia) and political departments (politotdely) in 1957-1963; lists of people dispatched to work behind German lines by the TsK KP(b) of Belorussia, Latvia, Lithuania, Moldavia, Estonia, and the Karelo-Finnish SSR, Arkhangeslkii, Voronezhskii, Vologodskii, Kalininskii Krymskii, Kurskii, Leningradskii, Murmanskii, Orlovskii, Smolenskii, and Stalingradskii obkoms (VKP(b), and by Krasnodarskii and Ordzhonikidzevskii kraikoms (VKP(b) in 1942-1944; list of party and Komsomol members from Stavropolskii krai (territory) who returned after performing special tasks; list of party members dispatched by the TsK KP(b) of Ukraine to work behind German lines and of party members (partiinye rabotniki) who were ordered to stay in Ukraine under German occupation; lists of party members performing special tasks, and correspondence of the Department of Budget and Finance of the Administration of Affairs of the TsK VKP(b) with the central committee of KP of union republics and okoms VKP(b) that had dispatched the said people to perform special tasks, 1942-1944 and 1957-1963 (Reel 2.451, File 136-159)
    - Lists of party members dispatched to perform special tasks by Vologodskii, Murmanskii, Rostovskii, and Gorkovskii obkoms, by the TsK KP(b) of Belorussia and Latvia, and by Stavropolskii kraikom VKP(b); lists of people performing special tasks, whose families get allowance via Central, Belorussian, and Lithuanian headquarters of partisan movement; lists of party members (partiinye rabotniki) currently fighting in partisan detachments submitted to the TsK VKP(b) by obkoms and central committees of union republics where the families of the said party members reside; lists of party members dispatched to perform special tasks, and correspondence of the Department of Budget and Finance of the Administration of Affairs of the TsK VKP(b with central committees of the communist parties of republics and obkoms where the families of the said party members resided; correspondence of the Department of Budget and Finance of the Administration of Affairs of the TsK VKP(b) with central committees of the communist parties of union republics and obkoms regarding payment of wages to those who previously worked for party and Soviet organizations or in the field of economies ( rabotniki) dispatched behind German lines and re payment of allowances to their families; the same correspondence with attached applications and reports, 1942-1945 (Reel 2.452, File 160-172)
    - Correspondence of the Department of Budget and Finance of the Administration of Affairs of the TsK VKP(b) with central committees of the communist parties of union republics and obkoms regarding payment of wages to those who previously worked for party and Soviet organizations or in the field of economies (khoziaistvennye rabotniki), and were dispatched behind German lines and re payment of allowances to their families, with attached applications and reports, 1942-1943 (Reel 2.453, File 172-177)
    - Same (Reel 2.454, File 178-182)
    - Same, 1943 (Reel 2.455, File 183-187)
    - Same, 1943-1944 (Reel 2.456, File 188-194)
    - Same, 1943-1944 (Reel 2.457, File 195-201)
    - Correspondence of the Department of Budget and Finance of the Administration of Affairs of the TsK VKP(b) with central committees of the communist parties of union republics and obkoms regarding payment of wages to those who previously worked for party and Soviet organizations or in the field of economies (khoziaistvennye rabotniki), and were dispatched behind German lines and re payment of allowances to their families, with attached applications and reports, 1943-1945 (Reel 2.458, File 201-207)
    - Same, 1944-1945 (Reel 2.459, File 208-215)
    - Same, 1942 and 1944-1946 (Reel 2.460, File 216-231)